Muhammad Faheem

Software Engineer

SUMMARY

A Software Developer, Scrum Master and a Machine Learning enthusiastic. Muhammad Faheem is an Azure developer, an Oracle Certified Financial Crime & Compliance Specialist and a Professional Scrum Master and has worked with numerous banks, both foreign and domestic

WORK EXPERIENCE

2018 -

Software Engineer

Present

ABN AMRO Bank N.V

Currently developing machine learning applications in the bank to counter Anti Money Laundering activities. This includes development of software on Azure cloud from scratch i.e. Software design, development life cycle, testing, automation, monitoring and production deployment.

Key roles include:

- Developing code for parallel big data processing using **Pyspark**, **SQL** and **Python** by leveraging **Azure Databricks.**. The code is written in an OOP way using design patterns
- Creating, monitoring and orchestrating data pipelines on Azure cloud using $\mbox{\bf Azure}$ $\mbox{\bf Data Factory}.$
- Creating data layers and managing data in Azure Storage for e.g. Azure Data Lake
- Performing **Unit testing**, Functional testing, Performance testing and Integration testing. This includes development of these testing frameworks as well.
- Performing code review and quality checks using Fortify, SonarQube and NexusIQ.
- Creating and automating pipelines in **Azure Devops**. This includes Build and Release pipelines, maintaining code in Azure repositories, documentation in Azure wiki, using Azure Test plans for functional testing, generating and publishing Junit reports, maintaining artifacts, and controlling all PaaS services/ deployments from a single place.
- Maintaining the machine learning stack i.e moving data from source to the Databricks Mlib pipelines.
- Maintaining the machine learning stack i.e moving data from source system to the Databricks MLlib pipelines.
- Source code version control using ${\bf Git}$
- Maintaining the Azure Stack which includes resource groups, resources and optimizations.
- Creating high level SQL analytical reports using **OBIEE**.

2017 - 2018

Senior Software Engineer - Financial Services

Techlogix

Worked as a full stack developer on Oracle OBDX (Oracle Banking Digital Experience) which is a hybrid internet banking application.

Key tasks include:

- · Creating front end using Oracle JET ,knockoutJS , Javascript ,SAS , HTML and CSS.
- Developing and consuming backend JAVA REST services.
- Developing high level SQL packages on Oracle Database.
- Mapping client requirements to the application development and configuration

2015 - 2017

Software Engineer

Techlogix

Worked on Oracle Financial Services Analytical Applications (OFSAA) for Financial Crime and Compliance Management (FCCM), formerly known as Mantas, OBIEE (Oracle business intelligence enterprise edition) for generation of reports, HOTSCAN for handling swift payments, and Compliance Link for customer batch screening.

Key tasks include:

- •ETL development using Java.
- · Conducting functional training and technical training to the client.
- Mapping client's requirements to scenarios



- Amsterdam, Netherlands

muhammad.faheem992@gmail.com

SKILLS

Python, Spark , SQL, Java, Git, Powershell, Bash

Azure Databricks, Azure Data Factory, Azure Devops, Azure Cloud, Data Engineering, Data pipelines

Unit testing, Functional testing, Performance testing, Integration testing, SDLC

Machine Learning -Regression, Classification: Logistic Regression, Decision Trees, SVM ,Clustering, DBSCAN

Intellij, Anaconda, MYSQL, Weblogic, Websphere, Oracle 11g, Tomcat, Toad, WinSCP, Pentaho DI, Netbeans, Visual Studio 2012, Eclipse

HTML , CSS , PHP ,Bootstrap, Javascript

Linux and Unix

C# , C , C++

ACHIEVEMENTS

First position in Speed Programming ITEC 2013 held at NED University

- · Creation of Custom KYC jobs to cater Central Bank's regulations
- Creation of Custom AML scenarios to cater Central Bank's regulations
- $\boldsymbol{\cdot}$ Performing Data Ingestion , generation of alerts,cases and reports (both on RR and OBIEE).

EDUCATION

2011 - 2015 **Bsc (Bachelors) Computer Science**

National University of Computer and Emerging Sciences

Graduated with a CGPA of 3.09.

2009 - 2011 A levels

Beacon House School System

Scored 1 A and 2 B's

I was awarded 100% scholarship due to my excellent performance in O' Levels

2007 - 2009 **O'Levels**

St. Pauls High School

Scored 7 A's and 4 B's in O levels (A was 90+)

The highlights of these were my exceptional marks in English, Mathematics,

Additional Mathematics and Accounting Finance

PROJECTS AND IMPLEMENTATIONS

GO-AML CTR Transaction System - National Bank of Pakistan

Implemented a C# based transaction capturing product which captures CTR transactions and converts them to XML files.

Google shopping scrapper. A scraper bot developed using selenium and Java swing that filters out the cheapest product available on google shopping based on the product name provided

Creation of Amazon Checkout scrapper.

A scraper bot that developed using selenium and C# Forms that automatically check outs products available on Amazon based on the product name and ASIN number

Friend's Circle

A Web application developed using php that shows the location and distance between friends.

File Hub

A Web application developed using php that is used for file storage and sharing.

YourDreamScraper

A scraping bot made using selenium that gathered data from Facebook.

Implementation of FCCM, Compliance Link and HOTSCAN- Dubai Islamic Bank Kenya, First Micro Finance Bank Afghanistan, Meezan Bank Pakistan, Muslim Commercial Bank Pakistan (MCB), Afghanistan International Bank (AIB)

ETL Development using Oracle Data Integration - Bank Al-Habib

Created custom mappings to transfer data from files into multiple databases using ODI.

Smart Security Guard (Final Year Project)

Development of Facial Detection and Recognition using Java CV.

CERTIFICATIONS

Oracle - Financial Crime & Compliance Management (FCCM) Implementation Specialist IBM Certified Machine Learning Engineer

Professional Scrum Master I







Second position in Speed programming SPARC 2012 held at Muhammad Ali Jinnah University

First position in HUNGAMA Drama Competition held at Fast Nuces

Second position Speed Mobile Application Development Dev Day 2014 held at Fast University

Winner IBA Sports League 2015 (Volley) Winner NUST Olympiad 2014 (Volley)

